Hello and welcome back to Lam Rim.
This is episode 9.
I call it: "Visit to the Center of the Sun".
We talked about something as big and powerful
as an atomic bomb that you use to clean a ketchup stain off your shirt or blouse.
And I'm not exaggerating.  I want you to think exactly like that.
Imagine this:
Today is Independence Day here in America.
We often have a picnic with the family then.
It's the height of summer,
and American children are eating hot dogs or hamburgers and putting too much ketchup on them, and then some ketchup drips onto their shirts.  Imagine
that the mother sends this shirt or blouse out into the middle of the sun to be cleaned.  To
clean a small red ketchup droplet.
I know it's a strange image,
but I want you to imagine it this way.
I don't know what else to compare it to.  No idea
.  Simply send a tiny object towards the center of the sun.
Today we will visit the center of the sun.
And I am pleased to announce that we have just reached the 3rd and final section of the Lam Rim,
the steps on the path to enlightenment.
Now we move on to the Bodhisattva activities:
the thinking and actions of a Bodhisattva,
a person with the highest motive: @KYES BU CHEN PO, which means:
person with a high motive.
Those of you who have been following this Lam Rim for 10 years
should be happy that you have persevered, and that I have persevered, until this final part!
We have reached the final part, the last third.
Now, the mathematicians among you should be thinking: Geshe-la,
you said earlier that we still have 25% to go.
Why is this the last third then?
And the answer is that Pabongka Rinpoche's treatment of the topics during the last two days of Lam Rim is too short.
His presentation on meditation and seeing emptiness,
the last two of the 6 completions, is not very long.
I don't know what happened.
It's possible that his sponsor came to him and said, "There's only enough food for two more days!
Hurry up!"
It is possible that he received a mystical message from Tara.
Or perhaps he had an appointment elsewhere.
But if you ask me, Pabongka Rinpoche kept the last two parts shorter because Je Tsongkhapa had already covered them in his great Lam Rim,
the Great Book on the Stages of the Path to Enlightenment, the Lam Rim Chenmo.
Tsongkhapa did it so brilliantly that I can practically imagine Pabongka Rinpoche saying: "
Guys, there really is no reason why I should teach this,
because Tsongkhapa has already taught it, and in an extraordinary way."
And there are many stories about how Tsongkhapa wrote these last two parts,
and I am pleased that we will be studying them together.
So we will conclude this Lam Rim series with great teachings on meditation and emptiness.
Therefore, this section about the stages on the path for people who have Bodhichitta,
for Bodhisattvas, is
not as long as it could be.  Let's
look at the Tibetan:
@ GSUM PA SKYES BU CHEN PO'I LAM GYI RIM PAR BLO SBYANG BA LA Let
us practice our heart in the stages of the path for people with high motivation,
for people who are Bodhisattvas.
@THEG CHEN GYI 'JUG SGO SEMS BSKYED KHO NAR BSTAN PA PHAN YON DANG BCAS PA
We will cover the lifestyle of a Bodhisattva
in 3 different steps.
1)
@ THEG CHEN GYI 'JUG SGO If you want to enter the Bodhisattva path, there is only one way to get there.
Specifically, by achieving a certain state of mind.
If you want to attain enlightenment, if you want the chance to attain enlightenment,
if you want the chance to help the world, then there is only one way:
You must develop Bodhichitta.
You must develop this desire to attain enlightenment in order to be able to help countless living beings.
Let me explain "countless" to you:
Bodhichitta is directed towards countless living beings.
It is not just aimed at all the people in your city, or all the people in your country, or all the people on this planet.
Free yourself!
If you want to send the virus to the center of the sun, if you want to visit the center of the sun,
then free yourself from this concept that we are only working for all people on this planet.
We don't do that!
Free yourself from this concept that we only want to help all fish, birds, and land animals.
We don't do that!  That's
not what this is about.
We are talking about the entire universe!
Today we decide: I want to help every living thing in the entire universe!
Every single virus,
bacterium,
whale,
every human being in the universe.
Go out at night, in Sedona, or outside of Sedona, Rim Rock is even better,
and look at the stars and imagine it.
So, 1) You cannot practice the lifestyle of a Bodhisattva if you do not extend your mind towards this goal.
And when you actually experience it,
which requires some practice,
when you actually send out your mind,
when you are actually able to develop Bodhichitta, then the things you have to do in this world are nothing!
They are nothing.  They are insignificant.
Helping everyone in this world is nothing.
It's simple.
@PHAN YON DANG BCAS PA means: Let me tell you about the advantages of thinking this way.  This is the first step.
@BYANG CHUB TU SEMS BSKYED PA'I TSUL.  This is step 2.
How do you achieve this breakthrough, this mental breakthrough?
How do you perceive an entire universe and all the beings within it,
and then develop love for them?
Is that even possible?
This is step 2.
Step 3: @SEMS BSKYED NAS SPYOD PA LA SLOB TSUL LO
We will learn to act like a Bodhisattva.
If you have developed this hope of becoming a Bodhisattva, then the question naturally arises:
What do I have to do practically now?
How do I spend the hours of my day if I want to act like a Bodhisattva?
What should I do?
What does my daily schedule look like?
Here comes the first point:
@DANG PO NI, DE LTAR SKYES BU CHUNG 'BRING GI SKABS SU NGES 'BYUNG GI BSAM PAS KUN NAS BSLANGS
After covering the stages on the path for people with low and medium motivation,
you should now at least feel
that this life is truly painful, truly a problem.
The virus simply makes this clear.
But that's how it's always been.
There has always been a virus called death.
This virus is new.  It's much smaller.
But at least now we're all thinking about it.
@ LHAG PA'I BSLAB PA GSUM LA 'BAD PAS
Then we should work on the 3 exceptional trainings:
Treat others kindly.
Spend time in meditation.
And strive to recognize that things do not come from themselves.
@'BAD PAS RANG GCIG PUS THAR BA'I GO 'PHANG THOB TZAM DANG 'KHOR BA LAS LDOG TZAM 'BYUNG
You yourself can reach Nirvana
and leave the wheel of life
if you practice these attitudes.
That will be possible for you!
We've already taught you that, we're done with that.
@ DE TZAM GYIS MI CHOG
But you must not stop there.  Do
n't stop there.
You can catch even bigger fish.
Much, much bigger fish.  Don't stop there!
@SPANG BYA THAMS CAD MA SPANGS
If you implement what I have taught you so far,
you will not cleanse your heart
of all the impurities that exist.
@THOB BYA YON TAN THAMS CAD KYANG YONGS SU MA RDZOGS PAS
and you have not yet attained all those highest spiritual qualities
that you can attain.
@MA RDZOGS PAS Therefore
@RANG DON DANG, GZHAN DON YANG NYI TSE BA LAS MI 'BYUNG
@NYI TSE BA is a very disturbing word here.
A very sad word.
You can work on these paths I have taught you so far,
on all the meditations I have taught you so far,
but the amount of good you will achieve for yourself and others
will only be a tiny part of what you have to do.
@NYI TSE BA means: It's only a tiny part of what you should be doing.
And by the way: This word is most often used in Tibetan to describe hell on earth.
That's very strange.  So there is
this great hell that people can end up in.
But I also always think about people who have a car accident, and the car explodes and they go up in flames.
In the scriptures this is called: @NYI TSI BA'I DMYAL BA,
a little piece of hell on this level.
On this level of reality.
So this term @NYI TSI BA means: only a tiny piece.
And here he says: You want to help yourself and you want to help others?
Everything I've taught you in the last 10 years is @NYI TSI BA.
It's just a tiny part of what you can do, and now we're ready for the big things.
But Geshe-la, why did we spend 10 years with @NYI TSI BA, on the little things?
Why didn't we start with the more important things right away?
Because the little things are the ladder by which you reach the higher things.
You cannot achieve the higher things if you do not do the other two parts.
If you do not practice all the stages of Lam Rim in the correct order,
you could never reach the Bodhisattva part.
So you can't just say: I don't want that.
It is part of the Bodhisattva's way of life to master the lower paths that led you to her.
And you never discard them.
You simply outgrow them.
@MI 'BYUNG ZHING SLAR THEG CHEN LA GZHI NAS 'JUG DGOS LA
There is this concept in Buddhism:
once you are ready,
and once you have the appropriate preparation,
you should dive directly into the lifestyle of a Bodhisattva,
because if you don't, you will have to do it again anyway.
Sooner or later you'll have to end up there.
Perhaps this life is necessary.
Perhaps it will happen later in this life.
Sometimes people come to me and say:
I want to take a break from this Dharma.
I feel like I need a break.
I have other things to do now.
I have this big project at work, or I have to take care of this family matter,
and I need to take a break.
I remember saying that to one of my teachers in India once.
45 years ago.
I said, "I need a break."
And he looked at me and said, "Okay, but you will come back."
You come back because there is no other way.
You're coming back.  You come back to him because you have to come back to him.  Life will bring you back to him.
Because that's life.
You need the Lam Rim.
Life will always bring you back to Lam Rim.  Unless you die.
And even then, it will eventually bring you back to him.
@SLAR means: You have to come back.  @ SLAR THEG CHEN LA GZHI NAS
@ GZHI NAS means: You will waste a lot of time if you have to come back to him.
So you might as well do it now, instead of having to come back later.
The next picture
shows something I want to do with you in this episode 9.
I call it "Visit to the Center of the Sun".
In this image
- I was looking for an image that roughly describes what it feels like to attain Bodhichitta -
so this image,
as we, Seiji and Tim, have noticed, looks
a bit New Age-like.
It looks like it was painted in Sedona, Arizona.
It feels a bit like New Age, but let me tell you: if you ever attain Bodhichitta,
then this is what it will feel like;
the image is close.  Can you leave it standing?  Just one more minute.
This picture isn't crazy, and it's not a hippie thing either.
When you attain Bodhichitta, true Bodhichitta, it feels exactly like this.
Perhaps you would like to copy the image.
We've already paid for it.
So you can use and store it at home.
You should have such an image with you, perhaps as a screensaver or on your mobile phone.
It comes pretty close to the feeling of attaining Bodhichitta.
I'd like to take you on a little trip, just for fun, maybe for 5 minutes.  Let
's revisit what it feels like
when you first achieve true Bodhichitta.
It is not about merely imagined or partial Bodhichitta.
Or the attempt to feel as if you have Bodhichitta.  We're talking about the real issue here.
If one day you directly see emptiness and directly experience Bodhichitta,
we'll simply look at that experience,
because it brings happiness.
It is an atomic bomb.
If you continue working on this feeling, on
how it feels when you persevere,
then that will contribute to the destruction of the virus.
I believe this will help to destroy the virus.
It's like a nuclear weapon.
And the virus is like the ketchup stain.  Imagine
, for just 5 minutes, what it feels like to achieve Bodhichitta.
Take 10 slow breaths.
Focus on exhaling, a long exhale, don't worry about inhaling, your body will breathe.
Now please imagine that you have just seen emptiness directly.
And now you come out of this direct perception
and return to what we can call normal meditation, which is still not back in this world.
You are in a deep state of meditation; you are still sitting on your cushion.
Your eyes are closed.
Then suddenly the image of your mother comes to mind.  It's your mother.
A very, very perfect picture of your mom.  A living picture.  It really is your mother.  The way
you remember her best.  That's exactly what
she looks like right now.  She's
looking at you.  She looks into your eyes.
Even though it feels like she's in the front part of your mind, she's looking into your eyes.
With great love and also with an expression of distress.  She urgently needs help.  She's
in trouble.  It's like
she's jumping off the Titanic or something,
and she's looking at you with these eyes.
She says: I need you, I need help.
Then you say aloud to her in your heart: "Don't worry, Mom, I'll take care of you."
I will be strong enough to take care of you.  Do not worry.
I will have the strength to help you.
And I will do it, I promise.
Then her image fades before your mind's eye,
and suddenly there is the image of your father.  You
see your father.
He has the same expression in his eyes.
Anticipation.  But also anxious.
With a questioning look: "Can you help me?"
Things in life are hard, life has become difficult.
You say, "Dad, don't worry. I'll take care of it!
I'm studying the Lam Rim.
I'm learning a lot about emptiness.
And I know for sure that I'll have the tools to help you soon.
Don't worry. I'll take care of it."
Please - you don't need to be afraid.
You don't need to worry.
I know what needs to be done: And I'm doing it!
Everything will be alright, don't worry!
Then perhaps an image of someone else in your life appears, someone close to you, your wife or husband or one of your children;
the image of this person appears in your mind.
Just her face.
She also looks at you and asks: "Can you help me? Things are bad, things are really bad!"
Things are deadly; there is no hope.  Can you help me?
You say, "I've got this, I'll take care of it. I can do this!
I'll have enough strength to take care of you.
You don't have to worry.
I know what's going on.
I understand your situation.
I know what this life is like.
I get it, and I'm going to take complete care of you. Do
n't worry. You really don't need to worry.
I'll take care of it."
Then that face fades, and then you can gradually imagine other faces of people you know.
Close friends, family.
Uncles and aunts.
Brothers, sisters.
Nephews and nieces.
One by one, they appear, and you comfort them.
You say, "I'm really going to take care of it."   "
You don't need to worry."
In this way, you go through all the people you know
and all the people you've ever met in your life.
Then you start to consider all the people you haven't met yet and all the people in this world.
Begin with your neighbors.
Go through the whole city, and sure, you can't look at every single person.
But take one person here and there.
Extend that to the shores of the continent
you live on.
Look at them all.
Then go even further.
To other continents.
In this way, you reach all the people in the world.
While you're still sitting here.
Then you can begin with the animals of this world, with the fish.
I'm not talking about specific species here:
I'm talking about helping every single animal.
Each one is looking at you. Each one is expectant.
Each one is afraid.
Each one receives your personal promise:
"It's my turn."  “I’ll take care of it.”
Imagine every single creature, tiny creatures at the bottom of the sea.
Tiny living beings in your bloodstream.
Meet each one.
Talk to them.
When you’ve finished with all the living things on this world, then start on the next world.
I don’t know where the next world is. Alpha Centauri? It’s
probably many light-years away.
Go there and do the same meditation for everyone on that world.
In this way, you reach all the worlds in the entire universe.
And the karma of meeting 7 billion people, one by one,
and trillions of other creatures, on one planet,
and then on all the planets that exist,
countless planets,
meeting all the beings there,
that is Bodhichitta!
That is the direct experience of Bodhichitta.
If you can, in this episode,
simply develop this feeling,
then you don’t have to worry about yourself.
You don’t have to worry about your family.
You don’t have to worry about your country.
And you don’t have to worry about a  A world overrun by the virus. These are small things!
And we will take care of them too: because
we are working on a bigger project.
We are working to help an entire universe!
Countless billions of beings.
Countless billions of animals and other creatures.
We have this ability. You have this ability.
I pray that you may attain it in this lifetime.
I pray that you may awaken it in this lifetime.
Your mind already possesses the ability to touch every living being and promise it that you will care for it.
The purpose of this Lam Rim,
the purpose of this retreat,
is something like the journey to the center of the sun.
Think of every living being.
Countless living beings in a universe without limits.
Meet them, one by one.
Give each one, one by one, your promise.
This is what happens during the first direct experience of bodhichitta.
This really happens. This is what it feels like
.
If you keep visualizing it, it will help it to really happen.
Really! So
it is up to you,  If you truly want this,
if you truly want to be a true Bodhisattva,
then practice! Practice this visualization once or twice every day!
Whenever you have a few minutes.
Just imagine it, in your mind's eye!
And this will help it happen:
You will achieve Bodhichitta!
And for such a Bodhisattva, something like the virus won't be a big deal at all.
Just a tiny little thing!
Earning money.
Securing a livelihood.
Feeding the family.
Finding an apartment.
All of these are unimaginable trifles. They are nothing!
Your mind, your heart is like the center of the sun.
And a few cookies, a few Coca-Colas at the center of the sun, that is truly meaningless.
These things are not important.
Strive for the big thing!
Everything else is small in comparison.
And then everything else will become effortless. Easy!
That is Bodhichitta.
See you in the next episode.
Episode 10